this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online a computer org slash
software hello everyone this is Felina
for SE radio today with me from running
Catalina
Veronica is assistant professor at the
medical image analysis group at angle
University of Technology before that she
was a postdoc at a biomedical imaging
group in Rotterdam
Veronica is a PhD in pattern recognition
from Delft University of Technology her
research focuses on machine learning in
medical image analysis Veronica
welcome to the show thank you thanks for
having me happy - after to join the
podcast okay so the topic of today is
image recognition and let's start off
with with the basics what exactly is
image recognition I would say it's a set
of techniques based on machine learning
mainly that help us analyze images
automatically maybe another name I would
use this computer vision that's a bit
broader because recognition for me
really means to to assign a category to
to an image so for example if you would
tag a photo on Facebook with your
friend's name you've recognized the
image as being that person but you could
also think about more related tasks for
example finding similar pictures if you
are searching for let's say clothes or
cars that you like so that would be
retrieval and that's a different type of
task than recognition
okay so let me summarize there's a broad
field called computer vision yes in
which are different things that you do
with pictures and if you're recognizing
a picture then it's image recognition
and other things like suggestion similar
things are computer vision but are no
image recognition yes correct
okay perfect great
so you already mentioned that this is a
technique based on machine learning we
had a few episodes recently about
machine learning that we will link to in
the show notes but can you explain to us
how is machine learning related to image
recognition sure you could you could
think about image recognition program
without any machine learning that is
just doing image matching so for example
it would have a set of images it knows
and then when it tries to recognize a
new image it would just try to exactly
match that new image to its database
okay so that would do be something like
a pixel by pixel compares for example
okay so that would be matching there's
not no really learning going on there
and what we want to do with machine
learning is that say we have a database
of cats and we want to find more images
of cats online what we want to do is we
learn from the images we have a more
general idea of what a cat looks like so
even if the new image that we see on the
internet doesn't pixel by pixel look
exactly the same as our database we can
still learn to to recognize it so in
terms of machine learning that would be
a classification algorithm because we
have a class of things that are a cats
or pictures of the cats and it's trying
to classify pictures yes exactly right
are there other forms of machine
learning algorithms that our listeners
might be familiar with something like
clustering for example is this also
something that occurs in image
recognition where you would have
unsupervised learning and an algorithm
says these pictures are alike even
though it doesn't really know what the
category is yeah that's very very
possible so then rather than relying
learning a model of different different
types of pictures you have like cats you
just take all of your pictures and you
see which of them are more similar to
each other you see if they're groups
emerging another term that listeners
might hear here and there is image
processing
is image processing the same as image
recognition well I think the two are
related because you could use image
processing to enhance your images
somehow before you do the recognition
steps but image processing can also be
used standalone if you want to for
example if you have old photographs that
you scanned in and you want to remove
remove the stains or the wrinkles of the
paper that would be perhaps an image
processing technique and no learning is
being done no recognition or a filter on
the Instagram is that image processing
also yes and no I think very simple
filters would be image processing
filters but smarter filters like adding
something to the image that has to adapt
to the shape of your face for example I
think there's already machine learning
involved because the filter first has to
recognize where your face is in the
image and then kind of adapt to the
picture yeah okay so snapchat rainbow
moments would be image processing rather
would the image recognition rather than
image processing I have never seen this
but it sounds like something that you'd
need to at least detect the face image
it makes rainbow for me to come out okay
let's go back to more serious image
processing then what are typical
questions that image recognition answers
we already talked about is this a cat in
the picture what other big groups of
questions are there that you can answer
with this technique yeah so you can
label a whole image with a with a
category like the cat you can also
become more fine-grain so for example
you want to get a bounding box of where
each cat in the image is or even even
more fine-grain that you get an outline
of the cat of course maybe for forecasts
this is not so interesting but for
example if they can like it medical
imaging that I'm working in we might
want to outline different organs in in
medical scans and then we would like to
be very precise so we want to have an
outline rather than
bounding box you can have more than just
two categories so rather than saying
it's a cat or it's not a cat you can
assign multiple labels to the image for
example all the objects that you see and
more recently this this is now being
extended into assigning image captions
to the image so rather than just saying
cat and water you would get a label like
a cat is drinking water for example and
there are these websites where you can
upload a picture and it automatically
generates a description like that yes
actually may be interesting to know that
most of us are participating in creating
training data for for these kind of
things because every time you write your
label your pictures on Facebook or
Flickr this is mined by algorithms which
are learning to to improve their own
recognition no interesting so we are all
helping image recognition yeah it's a
type of crowdsourcing so we've already
talked about just upon a few fields
where information retrieval could be
useful but what are some of the fields
where it has already been applied for
example maybe some field that our
listeners are all familiar with is OCR
automatically recognizing handwriting
and processing that into phones is a
field where we are already very far what
are some other examples yeah so in in
your camera you probably have if you if
you're taking pictures of people you
already probably have like a little
square that shows up around people's
faces so this is a face face detection
and inaction so basically it just
searches for patches of the image where
there's a there's a face and it shows to
you the most likely candidate so that's
a two class problem is it a face or not
you can also have face recognition so if
you are tagging people Facebook might
already suggest to you who the person is
based on previous pictures that you've
tagged of that person you know so of
course I'm thinking of the new iPhone
that is a
to scan your face and see if it's
actually you is that related to or is
that way more advanced well it's it's
related in a sense I think that it would
look for similar character it would use
similar characteristics but it's a
different kind of problem because it
doesn't need to have a big database of
who it could be
it's a two class problem of is it you or
not okay and some other fields I'm
thinking security maybe it's a field but
we are quite far already in using images
in various ways yeah so handwriting
recognition or fingerprint matching and
also like by biometric type things like
like your face I I do think I'm not an
expert in this topic what I do think
these algorithms can sometimes be fooled
so if you show show to the to the
algorithm a picture or a video sometimes
they can easily be tricked into thinking
it's you but you don't have to actually
be there categorizing images that you
upload to apps so for example I recently
was selling some some things in my house
and I think I sold some shoes and when I
uploaded the picture that's the first
step you do online shop with the online
marketplace app mark plots it was
already suggesting to me that I should
put this in the category shoes also for
example apps for beer and wine like
untapped for beer and I think Vivino for
wine you can scan the label and then it
matches it to a database so this is a
bit more like the the matching problem
but of course because you take the
pictures as a different angle and
different lighting it's a bit more
advanced than just matching pixel by
pixel
well I've mentioned already medical
imaging that I'm working in so we we
have different tasks like for instance
just segmenting an image into different
different parts like different organs so
this is creating outlines of each organ
or we can think about more diagnostic
purposes like detecting potential
abnormalities which then will be shown
to an expert
of course self-driving cars need to
understand what they see so they need to
have a pedestrian detection on the car
detection interpreting road signs which
would also be more like a matching
algorithm
yeah that's there's a lot of things I
think in in in in most things you can
think of how to apply such a such an
algorithm yeah if you think about the
possibilities you're seeing roll
yourself okay so everything you see I'm
just looking around in my house I'm like
Oh an algorithm could recognize if the
curtains are open or if my door is
locked it there's there are plenty of
possibilities okay we talked about
fields where image recognition is
applied now but what are some fields
where you think it's going to be applied
soon or it could be applied soon yeah so
the idea I think pretty cool things both
good and bad so right now when the the
algorithms are learning they get a
pretty good idea of what the underlying
structure of the images is so they're
able actually to generate more images
that look like that so if you show it
tens of thousands of cats it can create
more cats there's even a website I think
we can find this for the show notes
where you draw an outline of a cat and
it fills in kind of the colors by itself
based on what it's learned and it knows
where to put the eyes and everything
yeah you can even do you could do pretty
scary things with this so if you would
be able to put faces of some people on
some other people you could create all
sorts of fake news that would look
realistic or a revenge porn yeah I think
many other probably not not very nice
consequences so you see more dangers in
the generation of these fake images put
together cats then you see opportunities
to do good well I'm not sure maybe it's
what what's more talked about in the in
the news right now if you if you read
sort of about the
the dangers of AI etc but yeah I can
think of also of some of some nice
applications so for example if I'm
buying clothes I would ideally like to
to have an image generated of how they
would look on me without having to buy
the first and then send them back or a
really cool thing happening in medical
images is that we can learn to
synthesize one modality from the other
so we can for example synthesize CT so
cat scan from Anna Mars cam which is
very good because in mr that it's it's
safer and city you get you get a dose of
radiation so you cannot always do that
for example for babies so that would be
really cool if we can learn to generate
one from the other so you can convert
one image that is less precise to a more
precise or a better image
yeah because right now MRI doesn't see
everything that that we need but there
might be hints in there which we do not
see but which with with with learning so
you would need coupled MRI CT scans the
algorithms can learn to fill in those
missing details oh nice so that's a
really positive application of the
generation of images rather than a
recognition of family yes okay so now
we're all very excited about the
applications of these techniques and we
want to get started what are some of the
core principles that you need to learn
about in order to be able to use image
recognition yourself what do we need to
know I think the most important thing is
how you want to represent your images
what I mean by that is while images
there is they come in all sorts of sizes
and so it's let's take as an example
let's take apples and pears I'd say what
a recognized fruit so how this was done
traditionally is that we would think of
some visual features that for us can
represent the fruit and that would help
us discriminate the two so you would
think form for apples and pears yes
shape yes so for example for the app
you could measure measure its length in
different directions and it would be
symmetric and the pair has different
lengths and different directions so
those would be two feet two high level
features which we thought of because we
know how apples and pears look like and
based on just that maybe we can already
do a good classification and then just
to help me understand the pros the high
level process would be I have a lot of
pictures I define a feature that I want
to look at the shape and the length and
the height ratio I transform the picture
into a list of height and width and then
I'm going to do the classification on
that list yeah I'm not really on the
picture yes so there is an extraction
step and then there is the real machine
learning step yeah exactly so the
feature extraction then then you put
each image into what we call a feature
vector so that's just some numbers which
represent that image so like shape and
then on those feature vectors we can
train an algorithm to distinguish
different categories more recently
though this this has been moving so
that's what this is a really high level
representation of the data for what you
need some kind of prior knowledge about
apples and pears but if you have some
data that you don't really know what the
things are that you're looking for you
have to think of other ways to extract
this feature vector and more recently
with with deep learning techniques this
is now being done more or less
automatically from the data so it takes
is a representation just the pixels and
learns by itself what patterns of pixels
to look at which are discriminative for
the classes in the data so maybe nope
all our listeners are aware exactly over
deep learning is is there an explanation
for what exactly deep learning is it's
just the type of machine learning and
the deep refers to that when you combine
these pixels in different ways there's
there several steps into it any several
steps they this refers to the
okay so rather than the ones feature
extraction stuff we had before now there
are multiple steps in the process yeah
okay good
what are some of the issues or common
problems that we could run into so
suppose we have this apples and pears
Dana says or we have cats and we want to
know how to make more cats what could
possibly go wrong
I think a problem that happens very
often is overfitting what this means is
that you have had too little data to
learn the true patterns on it so say
you're learning to distinguish cats from
dogs but you have a very small data set
taken of of your own pets in your house
it could be that the algorithm then
learns to actually detect your couch
because your cat always sits on your
couch and not actually has learned the
cat representation it will always learn
learn something and it may seem correct
if you test it again on your own photos
but if you would test it on photos of
cats and dogs in the real world it would
do very poorly and that is what
overfitting means that the algorithm is
very much tied to the data and isn't
applicable to a bigger different data
sets precisely so it has over phases and
it has not generalized are there other
issues that we could run into I think
this is really the the main the main one
how you would you could try to overcome
this of course gathering more data more
diverse data so cats from
different cameras different types of
environment and also when you are
developing your algorithm you have to
make sure you're not secretly cheating
yourself so you would have training date
on which you develop an algorithm and
test days on what you test how it does
but if you do this multiple times and
you notice that the performance of the
test data is becoming better you're kind
of tweaking the algorithm and you're
going through the step several times
although you're using two data sets
training a test which looks like you're
doing things correctly you're actually
overfitting yourself
the data you have seen got it okay so
suppose we want to apply this in a
business setting because the examples of
the cats make me in little bits for fun
what type of business problems are
suitable how do we know how to recognize
a problem where image recognition might
be of use yeah so let's say if we focus
on categorization problems or
recognition problems you would need to
think about the kind of categories you
have how many are there
so is it recognition problem like binary
like is it this or not or is it or is it
a very large set of categories so the
first one is simpler than when the
number of categories is large you should
also think whether what you think makes
for similar images or images of the same
category if that's based more on visual
characteristics of the image or more on
some kind of higher level idea for
example if I'm working with images of
people faced face detection okay our
faces are different but there are very
common characteristics in each face that
there's a round head and two eyes setter
etcetera faces from not faces is easy
but let's say you would be interested in
faces of actresses from faces of not
actresses this is a much more difficult
problem because actresses come in all
shapes and sizes and non actresses come
in all shapes and sizes so that's that
knowledge is not really in the image
yeah then you would need external data
like I am the bee for example a big data
set of who is an actress would it be
feasible yeah I think so but then you
don't learn too from the faces how to
generalize to let's say new actresses
yeah of course you could you could you
could over fit by detecting the red
carpet behind the actress and the
beautiful gowns sure it's not something
I think we can we can
code yeah so the same goes for business
problems we have to think is the thing
we're representing really visible visual
or is it something that has different
meaning like maybe you can determine
between a good products and a broken
product but it would be harder to
distinguish between a new products and
it returns products because people could
return it because it's not broken also
beat it because they don't like it and
then there's no visual yeah that's
that's a good example here okay thanks
of course we've talked about it a lot
already there's not just the algorithms
there's also the data so suppose we want
to apply this in a business context what
type of data do we need you would like
ideally your data to be representative
to what the algorithm will encounter in
the real world and you want to have as
much data as possible to learn a good
model that generalizes and the doesn't
over fit so for example if you are
interested in doing kind of security and
recognizing who is where from security
camera it would be difficult for the
algorithm that you train it on like
passport pictures of those people
because that's just like one view with
very nice light lightning and in the
test environment it would be black and
white very pixelated photos so then it
becomes then it becomes harder yeah so
it has to be realistic not just of the
topics because a passport photo would be
a realistic of the person you know it
has to be realistic of the setting is
there any sort of feeling you could give
us for the size of the data sets when we
have enough data for information for
image recognition to make sense ten
pictures a million pictures a billion
pictures is there anything that make
sense as a number well I would say ten
is probably definitely too little but
during my PhD I've worked with data sets
that were less than 100 okay it also
depends on how difficult the task is in
the sense of well like this video are
you learning some simple visual
or is it a more high-level thing and
also on how many categories you have so
for for two categories maybe hundred
pictures is okay if you're learning to
distinguish cats from not cats but if
you're doing if you want to describe all
the objects in the image then of course
it will it will not be enough so
computer vision datasets now I think
have at least a thousand images probably
a hundred thousand a million that's the
smaller size and I think the the
state-of-the-art algorithms now they're
trained on this kind of web mind data
which you and I have helped annotate as
well but even still you're saying that
there's some hope for people that work
maybe for a small company or
medium-sized company we don't all have
to be Facebook and have to have that
much data in order to be able to do some
image recognition maybe with a hundred
or a thousand pictures if you were doing
simply simple things it's still a
possibility that's that lies in our
realm of yeah definitely I think so
especially if you have a quite a
concrete problem that you're solving
what's also popular now is that these
deep learning networks which learn
subjects so they need the most data so
these deep area networks that have
learned to recognize general everyday
objects to take those networks and to
kind of not train the algorithm from
scratch but train it from the point that
it has already learned what kind of
things are what kind of visual features
are important in images in general so
these networks kind of already know that
edges usually mean that one thing stops
and another thing begins so they can
build upon each other how much so so
that's something called transfer
learning so like rather than training
the algorithm from scratch you are
taking skills it already has and
applying them elsewhere so sometimes you
use an example of hockey if you have
played soccer before then you don't have
to although the rules are different in
the game is different there are some
general principles that
apply as well so you're not starting
from from zero and this would go for
pictures of hockey and hockey and soccer
maybe as well if an algorithm knows
where to find the ball in soccer it
might be useful that to use that
knowledge to find the the perk in hockey
or the ball in hockey because you'd be
on a similar place between people on the
ground great yeah yeah that's a really
nice example also in between you
mentioned the deep learning algorithms
need the most data why is that is that
because Aaron supervised learning
there's a there's an unsupervised and a
supervised part but let's maybe not get
into that detail but because they need
to figure out kind of from the bottom
how to let's say how to combine how to
weigh the different pixels in the end to
get to the category layers because they
don't have the features yeah they don't
have the this high level knowledge that
we gave them from the start and actually
now it's they can still over fit even
with with lots of data so there are some
examples now online where these networks
have learned to recognize let's say cats
and dogs but you can fool these networks
by changing one pixel in the image and
then the label that the network gives
changes even though for for us of course
it would it would never happen and the
funny thing is is that with these let's
say traditional features which are sort
of out of fashion now this would have
never happened because the pixel is
exactly the kind of noise that those
high level features learn to ignore
yeah like the shape of your Apple is
that one fake one green pixel outside of
the Apple but yeah nothing would happen
nothing would happen okay so the deep
learning is it isn't all hallelujah
fantastic there are some intricacies
still there also yeah exactly that's
that's good to know I guess so what
about a resolution of pictures suppose
we want to do something again in the
context of foreign companies do we need
great pictures from the newest iPhone or
could we also do useful things with old
phones or security cameras things like
that yeah I think many things are
possible I think mainly I work on images
which are which are
that knocketh modern and and higher
solution and and color again it mainly
depends on what you want to do with it
security food is just fine if you want
to analyze security footage but notes if
you want to do rightly different yeah if
you have so much if you have some
represents the data that somebody has
labeled I think you can definitely do
things okay talking about labeling what
are some issues that the data could
suffer from do the labels always need to
be perfect or is it okay if data is
mislabeled here and there how do you
handle the data when you're working with
the algorithms yeah so often it is
indeed assumed that the labels are
perfect I think most algorithms can can
deal with a certain amount of of noise
as well but it's not unlimited so where
when a photo that we clearly think is a
cat but it's labeled as as dog and we're
teaching somebody somebody else we would
clearly say oh no I cannot use this as a
training example
but for yeah for the algorithm it's it's
all the same so as a starting point if
many many images are mislabeled
yeah it's garbage in garbage out I guess
so do you manually sample the data set
before is this something that people do
or they just assume it will be fine and
if it's not they look at the data then
well it depends where your where your
labels come from right so it's possible
that you hired some students to label
the data it's possible that you put the
data on Amazon Mechanical Turk and you
underpaid people at I think it recently
came out two dollars an hour to label
some images yet depending depending on
the context in the application yeah how
do you know what the algorithm is paying
attention to and here of course we're
specifically talking about the deep
learning techniques if you don't have
the features is there some way to get
the features back from the deep learning
algorithm
that it can tell us well I know it's a
cat because it has two eyes and a nose
or is this information hidden in the
network but in a way such that we mere
humans can't understand it yeah you can
you can visualize in the image which
pixels are receiving high weights okay
so so if if it's indeed cats you would
see that and if it's learn to recognize
cats correctly you would perhaps see
that those those pixels are more
important but I think if you are
learning sort of more difficult concepts
your detection will not necessarily make
sense so if you are learning that you
are on the beach so you would need
several things for that you would need
to see some sand probably needs to see
some water maybe some people and bathing
costumes so then I'm actually not not
sure what would happen it's not like
there's one thing in the image that
makes it that category yeah and there
could be features also with a beach in
the horizon and things that aren't
necessarily just one pixel but yeah
shape in the picture like a future okay
so sometimes we know and sometimes it's
a bit more fake yeah and you would still
I think need to encode although the
promises okay with deep learning you can
completely learn everything from the
data I think you would still need to
encode how large is the area that you
are looking for approximately so if
you're looking for this like one
specific object like a cat or something
more more general yeah or a picture of a
beach which would be the entire picture
because yeah or that you would need to
pay attention to multiple regions for
for the label to be correct okay so
suppose we do want to get into this
are there any programming languages or
systems that are more suitable or very
useful or will any programming language
to do I think with the most languages
you if you have to use that language
because that's the language that
everything else you're doing runs on I
think it should be possible now suppose
we have a greenfield project and we can
whatever is best according to you then I
would say probably Python is the the
most popular choice because well you can
stop open source and there's many many
toolboxes and tutorials on how to use it
I actually use MATLAB most of the time
for let's say historical reasons because
of medical imaging and it's it's just
very nice for rapid prototyping but it's
not something that I would use if I were
building software that had to work on a
mobile phone for example so it also
depends on where you want to deploy the
algorithm yeah sure
and talking about those libraries where
you mentioned that they are available
for example for Python is it easy or
advisable to use different libraries or
would you say that it's not that hard
and it's better or easier to build
systems or algorithms yourself yeah
there's a bit of a trade of there I
would definitely advise for if you want
to build something that is robust to use
existing to rely on existing libraries
at the same time I think it's good for
if you're trying to understand what's
happening under the hood to try to build
a few simple things from scratch so for
example like this feature extraction and
a simple classification algorithm so you
kind of see what the algorithm is doing
and what goes wrong and this is really a
possibility I mean it's not way too hard
to build an algorithm like like that no
I think it should be it should be okay I
mean you you need an example that's
that's been worked out before by
somebody so you know that you know it is
possible to to recognize the things and
there are things some websites where
there are already data sets of pictures
and labels that you could just use and
play with right yeah so a common one I'm
not actually sure where to download it
but we can look it up is the nist digits
so these are just OCR digits from 0 to 9
and you have to recognize which digit it
is so this is off quite often used for
education
there of course it's also nice because
you can you can actually look at which
pixels it's paying attention to so you
can see what's what's going wrong nice
we will make sure to look up the link
and add it to the show notes yeah any
other data sets that we could play with
there are a few computer vision ones of
recognizing everyday objects imagenet is
one Pascal and a few a few others which
are acronyms so I'll have to google
those no problem we'll put them in the
notes as well because he's probably
exciting for our listeners yep try their
hand themselves with some datasets that
are not too complicated and as you were
saying that you know that it's possible
because sometimes some things like is it
a lamp or cactus maybe it's just too
hard and it's impossible to to try that
and that's probably a good first dataset
yeah and and for if you want to try
further there's cattle so they're
machine learning competitions are hosted
so it's not only images it's also other
datasets but there we are less certain
that it could work right yeah although
during the competition you will already
see the leaderboard of results so you
will have some idea of how how possible
it is and yeah there's even a website
with medical imaging data sets if
somebody wants to try this
it's called Grand Challenge dot org and
these are public data sets of for
example CT scans or Mars scans and the
tasks are to delineate organs or to
detect certain diseases yeah because of
course you yourself work in the medical
world where you use image recognition in
met in medicine can you talk a bit more
about that
why is medicine so suitable and what are
some of the problems that you are
solving yourself yeah so again there
different types of tasks as I just
mentioned so like delineating things and
the images like organs and this is
making the outline yeah yeah so this is
also called segmentation okay there's
more detection so you would try to
detect
of all possible tumors or possible
lesions so these would be candidates so
you will try to find bounding boxes
around suspicious spots and then of
course you want to detect more Yahoo you
want to detect more than they really are
you don't want to miss to miss any oh
yeah so you want to err on the side of
having too many yeah positives rather
than missing one exactly so then you
would have all these candidates and then
maybe you would do you would have an
expert go through them and say this is a
real candidate and this is not and then
you would do a second step of
classifying the the true tumors or
lesions from the incorrect detections
okay but you envision that there would
always be an expert in the process or do
you think in a future people just go
into a scanner and the results comes out
without any doctor present no I don't
really I don't really see that happening
I do see that I don't see no articles
about AI replacing doctors but I think
there are so many tasks which really
need to be automated and are not yet so
so there are still plenty of of doctors
but PhD students often who are
delineating things and the images which
should really be done but algorithm and
I mean this doesn't this is not a
diagnosis this is just seeing yeah so
for example if you want to measure
different different parts you want to
outline them in the image and this does
an algorithm can do but there's no
decision-making there like it means the
person has a disease or not but do you
think this is for ethical reasons or do
you just think that algorithms are not
good enough ever to be able to see the
things that are human eyes can see
so you mean why it's not internal
ultimate now being a pilot practice you
know why we can't envision a future
where it would be entirely human out of
the loop and just the algorithm is it
just impossible because we will always
see it or anything that an algorithm
pick up no I I do think that's also of
course algorithms can see see things
that that we cannot pick up on yeah and
also can take into account much more
much more data but I think there will
always be things that the algorithm
hasn't adapted to like like a disease
that has mutated and then nobody has
seen it before I mean the algorithm will
kind of be forced to give an answer
based on the categories it knows to give
and well it's not that the human doctors
will know from the first time what it is
but I think that's kind of the
distinction that once the machine
learning system has learned something
that's kind of it's it's world and it
cannot go go further to new problems so
then if the doctors would have to invent
invent something else and this is what
people have been doing so well for all
of history and what well some people I
think even must believes algorithm will
do this but but I don't yeah yeah this
of course something we hear in the news
all the time like AI is going to replace
whatever profession inserted it in the
headline now while well it's so possible
to fool algorithms with a single pixel I
don't I don't have those those fears and
it's good I guess at least for your
career it's probably good if you aren't
made obsolete but by algorithms if just
you are replaced by algorithms that
would be a bad thing so let's talk about
performance because if we think about
algorithms at least if I think about
algorithms and machine learning and deep
learning I think oh this is going to be
computationally expensive can these
algorithms run on your laptop or your
mobile phone or do you really run them
on a big cluster or somewhere in the
cloud how does that work I think for the
for the things I've worked on I'm never
I've never had really too big data
especially with medical images we often
know the problem that we have too few
scans to to analyze there's also the
distinction between training the Algar
and testing it so training and learning
the model can take quite a long time but
then the the testing so when you have
some new days that you want to
categorize that that is usually actually
quite quick there's not so much
computation that still needs to be done
it's just you take the the pics that you
go through the pixels you use the
weights combine them and out comes a
category let's say so the training is
expensive but actually classifying one
single image isn't very expensive yeah I
mean I wouldn't say that holds for for
all the algorithms but sure you can in
general yeah we just want to get an idea
of whether or not is applicable and what
type of things we need to think about
like investing in hardware so you're
saying if you just take a picture from
with your phone and want to have it
classified that's not necessarily going
to take a long time it's just a pre work
that is going to be potentially
expensive yeah and now I think also
there there are techniques if we are to
build an image recognition that it
doesn't for example go patch by patch
from the top left corner of the image
asking is is this what we're looking for
and then moves a pixel is this what
we're looking for I mean there are
smarter algorithms now that can can do
this and I think these are also included
in some toolboxes yeah this is what I
wanted to ask about actually if we have
huge images maybe you know pictures that
the Hubble telescope takes do you break
them up in pieces but I think what
you're saying here is you wouldn't break
them up in little small pieces but
rather you would scan them and zoom in
on the short-term region and then
analyze that am i understanding that
correctly yeah I was thinking about just
more general photos before because you
mentioned the the mobile phone with
really large images I'm not sure it
depends so if you're doing a detection
problem so let's say you are yeah
detecting some new galaxies or in these
large images if it doesn't matter what's
in what what one part of the image to
detect something in another part of the
image you can of course just split the
image up and
and processor to paralyze the the
processing yeah if they're unrelated
like different stars and you're not
looking for a galaxy but just separate
stars yeah yeah sure then you could
split it up yeah yeah sure we're looking
for one or multiple related things then
you say that that could be techniques
that you're scan the image maybe take a
few pixels to see where it could be yeah
I think that should be possible okay
this is good to know people that work on
large sets we've already talked about
algorithms which talks about data but
how will we learn this suppose we are
the people many people in our audience
are normal programmers and they want to
learn more about using image processing
or image recognition what are some
skills that you need to know do we need
a PhD and data visualization like you or
what do we need to learn I think it's
it's good to have some intuition of
these these feature vectors so how how
an image looks like and what happens if
you take what you think are similar
images and you represent them by some
numbers and how would you get this
intuition that's just drawing it out
yeah exactly so for example like with
these nice digits with these zero Taniya
because then you can even see what the
algorithm is paying attention to you can
see whether the digits you thought were
very similar actually have similar
feature vectors and so can be easily
classified by the algorithm and how
would you see that you would use some
sort of data visualization on the future
factors I guess you could Kuster them in
a 2d or 3d space oh yeah that make sense
and because because they're poor they're
little square pictures often people also
actually just put the put the picture
onto the plot so you would see okay so
here are the zeroes grouped and then
some other region of the plot the ones
are group III or or you would use
different different colors that's maybe
applicable for for all sorts of data
okay so I'm going to classify that as
sort of a a practical
analysis skill that you have some
intuition for that what your data is
doing yeah of course these things for me
I only have a PhD so for engineering so
for me already these things are sort of
scary it's algorithms and mathematics
and leaning and algebra do I need to
learn about new mathematics or and and
if so what type of things do I need to
learn about no you wouldn't need to
learn really new things maybe some
understanding of statistics helps so
like I mentioned before that cats often
on couches there's that's a correlation
of things but you don't you don't need
to be able to derive lots of things on
the board and also some idea of
optimization function optimization or
linear algebra so what is functional
optimization so so the algorithms they
when they have training data they try to
make as few errors as possible on this
training data given the the categories
and this this is this error that the
algorithms is making it's a it's a it's
a function of how well it is doing so
what the algorithm is actually trying to
do is to minimize to find the minimum of
this function so that would be the
parameters with which the algorithms
makes the least mistakes that is as
close as possible to get the real data
sense yes and well of course if you have
a convex function which means it's like
really nice and smooth just like like a
bowl or like like it's all squares yeah
like x squared if you have a convex
function like that you can just
calculate its minimum so you don't need
to do anything complicated but the
function that these algorithms optimize
are unfortunately not so nicely shaped
so they have all sorts of bumps and you
need other other techniques for that and
you also have to be aware that it can
find the local minimum so so the
algorithm thinks it's found a good
solution but in fact there
better solutions elsewhere yeah that
could be related maybe to the
overfitting yeah for example also guys
okay that sounds like it might be doable
for let's say normal people where would
I learn this can you give us a few
resources where to learn more about
image recognition there's a great
machine e-learning course on Coursera by
Andrew Inge so I think that's actually
how Coursera started this was the first
course he developed and only then
Coursera happened yeah and it's the
massively popular course there are
different tutorials depending on which
language you would like to use so so
there are some four for Python or for
math lab that I know I think also on
YouTube you can often find talks of
people demonstrating some application
there they are doing like tutorials as
well but I think Coursera is a great
place to start do they have a course
specifically about image recognition
also or would you just say do the
machine learning course and that's
applicable enough also to images yeah I
haven't I do think they have some
something more now there are also some
courses on deep learning but I haven't
done those so I'm not I'm not sure
whether to recommend those but I think
the machine learning course is a great
start okay thanks a lot
is there anything else you wanted to
share I think we've covered a lot about
image recognition the algorithms and
data are the skills what to do is there
anything you wanted to add to the show
yeah maybe I'm thinking about my
take-home messages that would be to
always be skeptical about your your
algorithm and look at your data and look
at the mistakes it's making because you
might be overfitting without without
knowing it hide some data from yourself
to test your algorithm oh I like that as
a very concrete yeah if you just hide a
little bit of theta you don't take it
into account at all and only once you've
you've designed an algorithm as you
think you're happy with exactly to bring
out the data oh you can see how how how
well you really did you how well you
really did yeah also I think don't
believe many hyped
girls about how algorithms are taking
over the world it's pretty hard to build
robust algorithms as we've seen with the
with the pixel example yeah so you
really see that as an aid to people oh
yes in place for no no definitely I
think it will replace some very boring
jobs which exist right now
I also if I if I have to sort my photos
I mean I know I could build an algorithm
but there isn't something that just very
quickly does the job for me like a paper
clip that says oh I see you're putting
the pictures with these are these people
together in a folder maybe because it's
their birthday shall I help you find all
the other pictures of this person I mean
I would really like that but that it's
it's it's not it's not there yet so I
know I think people shouldn't be scared
for their jobs and on that positive note
then Veronica thanks a lot for being on
the show we will make sure that we add
all the things you're promising the show
knows and also a link to your of course
your blog and because you're an avid
blogger and you're a trader profile so
people can learn more about all the
exciting things you're doing thanks for
being on the show thank you thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team at SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se Radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening
you